hello and welcome it's September 9th
2024 this is active inference art stream
number 3.1 with Diana omegi talking
about curious sounds prediction and the
human drive to engage with music there
will be a presentation and then we'll
read some comments and questions from
the live chat so thank you Diana for
joining and looking forward to your
presentation thank you Daniel for the
invitation and to everyone who's joined
today I'm uh a senior lecturer and um
researcher at gil University of London
and today I'll be talking uh giving a
talk that's entitled curious sounds
prediction and the human drive to engage
with music and the reason I chose this
title was because it recently came
across this
statistic um the International
Federation of the phonographic industry
do a report every year where they say
how much uh the the average person
listens to music and it turns out it's
about 20.7 hours a week um so if we
assume that people get about eight hours
of sleep a night then um then we're
looking at about a fifth of our waking
hours that the average person is
listening to music and it it struck me
that there's a really interesting
question here which is what is behind
this drive uh to engage with music this
this
scale and so what I'd like to do in
today's talk partly because um I wasn't
quite sure um who' be attending but I
assumed it would be people with lots of
different backgrounds and um uh yeah
what I decided to do was just present a
little bit about what neuroscientists um
have been finding out about the neural
substrates of Music perception and
pleasure we might assume that has
something to do with why we choose uh to
listen to music um I then wanted talk um
for a few minutes about um what the
predictive processing framework um could
explain to us uh or tell us about why it
is um that we our attention toward
stimul might uh change over time and
finally use what we've learned from
Neuroscience from the predictive um
processing coding framework
to to present a model basically of the
dynamics of extended engagement with
music so um that's a piece of work that
was published earlier this year and uh
which I'm you know Keen to to share with
uh interested parties let's think about
music perception and the things that we
do without even realizing how uh
powerful uh uh these things are so we
can spot wrong notes and music that we
hearing for the first time by wrong I
mean um yeah notes that were clearly not
intended by the performer um we can say
whether two Melodies are the same or
different again hold pieces sequences of
pictures and rhythms um in our memory
and compare
them we can recognize familiar pieces
even if they've been played differently
Different lyrics different instruments
and so on and so forth and we can
correctly predict how a piece of music
we've never heard before might unfold we
might be able to sing along to it even
if we're hearing it for the first time
and naturally um people have come up
with ideas as to what's going on why
this is all possible how this is all
possible for example in this model um
published in
203 um the idea was this acoustic input
comes in under goes some analysis
inevitably get separated out into its
sort of uh pitch uh components and
temporal components that you know
undergo further um processing um these
interface with some store of musical
phrases and um patterns that we've
experienced in the past and so on and so
forth um but of course this is a sort of
box and arrow model of
what makes sense as you know series of
processes when we look at the brain
we're looking at a network of
connections between subcortical
structures the auditory cortex so-called
belt and parab Bel areas around the
auditory cortex and we're looking beyond
that we're looking at sort of more
frontal parts of the brain that we know
are involved in some of the more complex
functions that um we we're able to do as
humans and what's interesting is that
when it comes to something like pitch
perception which um is obviously a very
important part of processing music in
lots and lots of different cultures um
we see that the electrophysiological
responses to pitch um in this case um
measured intracranially um are very much
in line with the principles of
predictive coding in other words um it's
been shown that early tonotopic
structures um feed information about
frequency to later areas where we seem
to have this abstract model of pitch um
being formed and predictive signals um
being sent back so we're seeing
something as fundamental as just
determining what pitch we're hearing um
um not something as fundamental not
surprisingly something as fundamental as
um Pitch perception um um seeming to
have this um follow this predictive
coding principle
most of us can do lots of things with
music recognize it discriminate uh
pieces of music um not everybody um is
able to to do these um everyday tasks so
um for
over you
know now two 200 years or almost 200
years um there have been reports or just
papers about um what we now call
congenital IM Museum sort of difficult
ulty making sense of music that can
manifest as difficulty discriminating
Melodies and recognizing um Melodies
that should be familiar all those things
I said we do so naturally um and it's
not surprising that when this was begun
to be researched in the early 2s that um
that it was considered perhaps a
disorder of fine grain pitch
discrimination some of the tasks
suggested that um the individuals who
had it um were struggling to say whether
a pitch had you know changed if it was
not a a very large interval that was
being presented however as more work
came out suggesting that this could um
that people with generally musia may
also have difficulties um um for pitch
memory or with pitch memory um the
question that arose is whether there
might be a more
General U mechanism that's sort of um
compromised or um um in in this in this
uh um condition
and so that was one of the questions I
was asking during my PhD um in yeah the
late 20 yeah the late
2000s um where I was lucky to um be at
the same institution as Marcus pierce
who' developed this statistical learning
model of musical expectations so um as a
statistical learning model which means
that it learns from the regularities in
the Corpus of music you give it and a
piece of music um as it unfolds and is
able to spit out these values um for any
given event in that um piece of music so
um information content how surprising um
an event a note should be to a list how
about what that incoming note uh will be
and using this um model was able to sort
of um quantify the surprise in every
single note that we were presenting uh
well in The Melodies that we were
presenting to our uh participants with
amum and participants with about and
were're able to show that a musics were
showing less evidence of sort of
prediction error signaling um in
response to the notes in these
Melodies um further work work later on
from um different Labs um corroborated
this um using um bam C of modeling on mg
data showing that there was indeed this
abnormal prediction error from auditory
to FAL areas in those with the amusia it
was shown that if you looked at resting
state activity the degree of connectiv
ity between frontal and temporal areas
was much reduced in those with um a
musia and um again around this time it
was coming out that um if you looked at
the structural connectivity the AR the
bundle of um axons that binds the temple
and paral cortex to inferior frontal
areas then there was also this was a
compromise in the structure or Integrity
of um of this mle of Ain suggesting that
there was um some sort of
underconnectivity between the front and
temporal areas um Superior temporal
inferior frontal areas of the brain and
in in musics and that this might be
materializing or manifesting um in uh AB
normal predictions error
signaling this is work I mean this idea
of STG and ifg needing to communicate
for for predictions and prediction error
signaling was something that had um was
being more and more supported than just
typical listeners and the range of um
electrophysiology and also um f studies
um but since you know you know those 20
years ago there's been yet more studies
showing that it's not just those areas
that seem to be tracking prediction
error or showing prediction error like
responses um we see that areas like the
that gyus and insula are also um
tracking the information content of
surprise of musical events which um you
know is a nice explanation for why these
kinds of events surprising events can
lead to so of physiological arous and
more um and more visceral um um
engagement and yeah in other work um
that we've done we've shown that again
the size of the prediction error
response is reflected in this case
reflected in people dilation response is
even modulated by the entropy of mus the
musical context so um it it mattered
whether or not what someone was
listening to was very predictable or not
whether they would show a prediction
error response and those of you who are
into active in we'll know that this
sounds a lot like sort of precision
waiting um
happening um just you know a couple more
words about music perception when we're
listening um we come with lots of
different backgrounds some of us um or
some people have
um you know musical training um and
therefore sort of musical expertise they
may or may not even have know how to
play the piece that they they're
listening to and in this study for
example it was shown that when a
musician was listening to a piece that
they just learned um compared to when
they hadn't learned it before or
compared to when someone who didn't know
how to play the piece was listening you
saw this frontal parietal motor related
Network being activated just speaking to
the fact that musical perception isn't
just um the processing of the acoustic
information but seems to um implicate or
recruit areas involved in movement and
motor planning um and just to point out
that yes it's always the case of um was
very often the case the musicians will
show more of this activity but um most
listeners when they are listening to a
piece of music will show engagement of
these um sensory motor areas and that
was just to um prepare you for this idea
that um that's coming out or has been
around for a while even
um um that music perception um involves
two Pathways um much like um speech and
language perception involves two
Pathways a so-called vental stream or
pathway uh where core auditory areas um
sort of move their information uh
towards of more inferior frontal areas
um allowing the formation storage of
sound patterns that can then allow the
registration of expectation violations
and a more dorsal stream involving
parial and um premotor dorsal prefrontal
cortices um allowing the temporal and
you know motor manipulation of
information um that's been stored in
working memory and allowing predictions
but not about what one is going to hear
but rather about when one is going to
hear to hear it so sort of more temporal
predictions um and now just switching to
you know to say say a few words about
musical pleasure and what um the sort of
body of neuroscientific literature um is
saying about this what it's you know
what um people have done in this area i'
would say most of the work has come from
on the lab of representor um and Mill
University in Canada um where in a very
important semal study um then PhD
student and salor they showed that um
yeah when we experience chills these
very pleasurable physiological um
arousing um experiences of pleasure um
during music listening when we
experience them we see activation of the
so-call ventral sprum of the dipl
energic network whereby the sort of
anticipation of this chill's um um um
sorry whereas the anticipation of the
chill's experience recruits this um
other part of the the strim which is the
dorsal strim so in effect showing that
um the experience of chills is um um of
pleasure during music um is recruiting
reward in areas but in actually quite
nuanced ways and that separate out the
anticipation from the actual experience
um so those were that was a study where
they got people to say what moments and
what pieces of music they experience
these um very pleasurable um
physiological uh Leal moments but in yes
another study um where they present
people with music that they'd never
heard before they were still able to
show that the pleasure people reported
in response to that music uh was
explainable by how much connectivity
they were seeing between the superior
temp FR irus and uh um and the ventral
striatum so they really um um stress the
importance of this connectivity in when
we're you know talking about musical uh
musical pleasure um one way to to see
whether um this hold holds true of
course to um find people who really
don't um experience pleasure in response
to music and honia means you know lack
of pleasure not experiencing pleasure
unless are people who and it's
associated with depression and other
sort of um conditions but um um around
the early 2010s they um um these
colleagues showed that there might be
some people out there who have normal
responses uh reward responses or find
lots of things in life rewarding but
just not music and so these people with
so-called music specific andonia seem to
be able to recognize and understand
music discriminate Melodies you know
predict what's going to happen next but
they failed to enjoy it and what they
were able to show was that indeed um
these individuals would show um normal
responses um to secondary rewards
physiological arous to secondary rewards
like money but indeed when they were
exposed to moments in music bit should
Tech should you know for most people um
be experienced as you know very chy and
very pleasurable and quite arousing and
they just they were able to show that
those anonia just didn't show those
kinds of
responses and importantly they were able
to show um that um when they look at
connectivity between the STG and vro
striatum that indeed this connectivity
was much reduced um for those with
anhedonia compared to those with you
know listening levels of pleasure and
those who really love music
um just to say that um in one case study
um published uh a year after this fun
functional connectivity study um they
showed that someone with severe case of
musical anhedonia showed much um reduced
connectivity between
the temporal Superior temporal diis and
the and NAC corroborating this idea that
um the connectivity between these areas
are um is important for reward and last
but not least on the topic of pleasure
um you know and yes another way of um
testing whether um this you know this
network or you know that I've been
describing is is important for music
listening um is to show that within a
given individual you can kind of turn
off and on the pleasure they experience
from music and again work from um the
very productive tutorial
um showed that if you stimulated the
dlpfc which is believed to stimulate the
striatum um then you'll show
um then um yeah you excitation um of
this the excitatory sort of um protocol
would lead to Greater liking willingness
to buy a piece of music that just been
heard and um increase in the arousal
demonstrated uh where conversely and
inhibiting that pathway so reducing stri
activity seems to reduce pleasure and
willingness to buy that piece of music
you just heard and and the physiological
responses um they were also able to show
that when you put people in the scanner
immediately after sort of um or around
the time they'd just had this
um this uh transal magnetic stimulation
applied um yes it was they a to show
that the degree of connectivity between
right AUD cortex inventure stum again
just this auditory cortex um reward area
connectivity um predicted the extent to
which they had shown enhancement of
pleasure from um from TMs excitation in
other words showing this length
between you know confirming that the
dlpfc was probably um stimulating
dorsals uh sorry striatum which was um
leading to uh more or less connectivity
with this STG which was leading to more
or less um
pleasure um but just round this section
of my talk um up what I've tried to do
show that when we're listening to music
the acoustic input is going through a a
series of
um um areas that are carrying out
processing at very different um
different stages and especially when we
get to sort of the inferior frontal gyus
and Superior Tempo drus we're looking at
we're seeing
um um the neural substrates of
prediction um predictions and prediction
error signaling and this seems to be
compromised in those with am and that
might explain the wide ranging
difficulties with music when we come to
speaking about pleasure um inevitably um
people speak about the role of the
auditory predict auditory system and its
you know capacity for prediction um but
they point out that um most important is
this um more important say even than the
STG and frontal temporal um or frontal
area connectivity is the you know
temporal area is involved in auditory
processing and the reward areas and this
seems to be compromise in those who
report much reduced um pleasure from
music and um I can really recommend a
book
called It's called but it was published
by zor in 2024 where he does a really um
lovely overview of the work that come
lots of work that's come out of his lab
and lab of and several labs around the
world trying to understand um you know
put together what we know about music
perception how sort of interfaces with
pleasure and beginning to tell us a
story around the role of um prediction
prediction um here but just to say that
you know my interest has always been um
trying to think about music listening as
more than just um emotions or pleasure
these are obviously things that are very
important to us but I've always had this
desire to understand the temporal
dynamics of our engagement with it and
you know Studies have shown and these
were have only come out since I've been
pondering this that as with many um
activities you know we will mind
wonderer a large proportion of the you
know the time that we think we're doing
that activity in this case music
listening and you know for most tracks
our engagement with a piece of music
will rain or just you know drop by quite
a bit within a few seconds and um it's
clear that music can attract our
attention it can keep us listening but
it can also lose us uh so will catch
attract our attention again and question
is when and why are we listening and uh
and when and why are we not listening
and I thought this is where um
predictive um coding framework and the
sort of active inference could maybe um
help us you know further our thinking on
this topic um and and so just to sort of
talk about music listening and um the
Dynamics of well talk about the Dynamics
of um attentional engagement um in these
terms
um if we think about the auditory system
and engagement in the auditory realm um
then well in general predictions in um
the prediction coding framework I said
to ascend this hierarchy that make for
better models that in turn allow us to
make better predictions and the auditory
system this is you know prediction erors
ascending from the thalamus to the
auditory cortex where um posterior
expectations you know are influenced by
prediction errors and send predictions
um
um that further inform these prediction
errors so there's this sort of low-level
processing of um um the information
that's coming in as we as we as we
listen to uh to anything
but I think what's nice is that the
predictive um sort of processing
framework acknowledges that we're not
you know always providing that same
amount of um well attention to every
incoming stimulus and in this framework
there's uh an explanation of where and
how attention um um happens why why it's
deployed and the idea is that um any
agent will look at how reliable data is
that um how reliable the data that's
coming in is in order to see whether
they should use that you know data to um
in their inferential processes um this
is you know known as position waiting
it's meant to be carried out by these um
neurom model cells that are different
from the cells that are carrying out the
actual um transmission of um um
predictions and prediction errors um but
simply put attention as scen as this
sort of deployment of high Precision or
confidence um in the beliefs about how
observations are related to our actual
States and it's said to enable us um and
what we hear to more greatly influence
our predictions and the interpretation
of the heard sounds um people have begun
to look at this idea of precision
waiting um and the extent of a
prediction error and the extent of which
it can be seen in
um uh neural data when people are
listening when people have varying
levels of expertise and therefore with
different generative models of the music
they're hearing when you know when
they're listening um what's happening
when they're listening to pieces of
music that are very predict predictable
versus less predictable and they be
begin began to be able to show that
indeed the connectivity within the
auditory ques within STG um are
reflecting um this idea of precision
waiting where you're able to um
basically upweight or provide sort of
more gain on the neurons that are
processing um um incoming information or
or
not um of course there moments we're
attending but the moments where we're
not attending and here as well um the
sort of literature coming out is
suggesting that there there are ways to
to account for this so um the role of
opaqueness has been suggested to be
quite important um in the me awareness
um of our attentional states where a
state is set to be opaque when it's
underlying processes can be attended to
um or visible to conscious awareness um
as such um if you talk about opaqueness
and attention and letter awareness so
attentional states are the second order
states that allow first order state to
become opaque whereas meta awareness and
the is the sort of third order state
above attention allows us to to allows
attentional States to become opaque but
generally the idea is that meta
awareness is possible thanks through
sort of more deep generative models
where you have this higher level that's
modulating the opaqueness of our
attentional state and allowing us to
distinguish when we're attending to the
sensory stimulus or uh compared to when
we're not and if we realize that we're
you know not attending we might want to
take mental action and this has been
described as um possible or inevitable
thanks to um this imperative active
inference imperative to to choose
actions that will bring us close closer
to our our preferred state so um if uh
the task we're carrying out or what
we're meant to be doing at that moment
is listening to the music or we've
decided that's what we should be doing
then the idea is um our generative
models preferred status the state of
attending and um so if we notice that we
are attending while we're attending this
shouldn't cause any surprise but if we
notice that we're not attending if we
notice we're mind wandering um this
should result in a surprise that under
the free energy principle should mean
that we need to minimize the surprise
and which means that we we there we
therefore attend so this um basically um
we're seeing how a met state of met
being able to have met awareness can
lead to mental action that can um lead
us to continue this process of attending
um but there's some situations where
um we want to actually take action
however small to to to that we will take
action however small to to really um
engage with you know stimul in the case
of in the a in the visual domain and
maybe um eye movements in the case of
hearing it's not always easy to see but
it could be you know talking out ear or
you know head movements to to to ensure
that we're getting the signal as best
possible um and basically here as well
we see an account of you know how
so-called curiosity what I'm calling
curiosity related behaviors U may come
about so the idea is that these
curiosity related behaviors uh are able
to resolve uncertainty um through the
choice of policies and through US
choosing policies that can reduce
uncertainty so if we uh main aim is to
reduce uncertainty then sometimes we
need to choose actions that will get us
there um and in this paper They carried
out some
simulations um where they showed the a
you know a given agent will choose
sometimes choose policies that by
exposing them to novel combinations of
states and outcomes
um could on the long run allow discovery
of how outcomes are generated and
improve um our models in the long run of
course curiosity is usually described as
a feeling you know um and um it's been
suggested that Curiosity could be seen
as this what it feels like when we
recognize that um there is uncertainty
out there that we can resolve by taking
action and just to point out that in
this study they in this paper rather
they um suggested that evaluation of
policies may be taking place in like the
C and pum which I think is quite
interesting given how these have been
involved or implicated in in the
anticipation of sort of pleasure that
people have also linked to some extent
to that wanting or
for an event or um or the a given
experience um and last but not least I
think no account of um music listening
is is is um complete without sort of
speaking to you know you know it's
capacity to to provide pleasure and um
the work coming out of the predictor
coding framework or act of inference
suggest that AFF effect isn't um just
the isn't related just to magnitude of
reward but to learning Dynamics where um
it's the result of Agents tracking
fluctuations in in how certain their
models are and it's been put um forward
that you know if curiosity is the
expected rate of reducing or minimizing
prediction error then affect could be
seen as um the actual rate at which
we're able to minimize um error where
this could be faster than expected and
lead to this sort of more positive
feelings that we can experience um in
different
contexts so suffice it to say that uh
the predictive coding framework you know
for for very long we've used it to sort
of account for prediction errors um
which was a real um priority for us in
music listening because they're very
easy to measure um or at least we see
these responses that can um we can pick
up very easily um and yes we have these
overarching theories about musical
expectancy and the role that plays in
our perception and ability to derive
emotion and meaning from music so
predictive cing framework has been very
influential as neuroscientists of Music
thought about um sort of music and
perception um but I think what's
exciting is how it's beginning to give
account of what's happening when we're
attending or you know this you know
distracted or mind wandering how meta
awareness um Can emerge or could take
place within this framework allowing
mental action allows us to reattend if
we realize we weren't attending and and
so on and so forth how we might um why
how and why um not how and why but
how um again curiosity related behaviors
could look in in this framework and and
why positive effect might emerge and I'd
suggest that all of these um
in some ways are as relevant when we
want to ask answer the question what is
behind this human drive to engage with
music so we could talk about pleasure um
which is what we've um tended to do in
the sort of Neuroscience of music world
but I would argue that there's all these
other um reasons which are very much
shared with information processing in
other domains and just as an aside if
anyone's wondering curious about music
how is that possible just to say that
we'd um just as a proof of concept we
did a few studies to show to see whether
people's um self of self-report of
curiosity made any sense in relation to
what was going on in the music and sure
enough um whenever they perceived often
when they perceived change people would
also report being a bit more curious
about what they were hearing um we were
able to show that people's curiosity
ratings when we probed them at different
points in a unfolding piece of music was
explainable by information content how
surprising that event was and that this
further was interacting with entropy
again to explain laain their um uh sort
of feelings of curiosity suggesting that
there was also this Precision waiting
mechanism going on there and just
because those two studies were um
looking only at self-reported music
linking that of curiosity linking that
to the music um but because it would be
nice to have another behavior that isn't
sort of self-report we looked at whether
um we would see what we thought would be
a negative relationship between mind
wondering and curiosity in the context
of music listening um and sure enough um
we showed that when people reported high
levels of curiosity about what they were
hearing they were less likely to um
report mind wandering at those moments I
could describe the Paradigm um if
anyone's interested but yes indeed we're
able to show that you're more likely to
be mind wandering when you're less
curious about when you report being less
curious about the music that you're
hearing you're more likely to be mind
wandering if you're less expert
otherwise in other words have more sorry
less musical training you're more likely
to be mind wandering if uh music at that
moment is quite complex or um more
entropic um but we saw that this
association between um mind wondering
and this tendency to mind Wonder more at
high entropy was reduced with expertise
so the more um you had musical training
or the more you seemed able to deal with
the complexity and not mind Wonder um
when you heard such complexity in music
and now just to finish with um short
presentation of this U model or
theoretical framework that we put
forward with with regard to um how
engagement with music um might look over
time and again this was just because um
after doing sort of some the only thing
I do but when I do music Neuroscience
studies um there's a tendency to use
quite short and um quite
um I don't know reduced stimul to as you
know pieces of stimul Mostly because we
have very clear H hypothesis and ideally
the stim the stimul are very easy to you
know they don't have too many
confounding things going on um that was
tended to be the case it's it's getting
better now we listen to sort of be used
to me they are more naturalistic that
you know go on for minutes but um in
that sort of um in that Spirit of what's
happening when we listen to a piece of
music or several pieces of music back to
back over several minutes in that Spirit
of what's Happening um we decided to
sort of put forward this um model um but
just to say you know what has been said
about music engagement and the
literature um um fairly new term hadn't
been really hasn't really been used much
um but when people have talked about
this idea of being engaged with a piece
of music or engaged in the context of
music listening they have tended to
emphasize this idea of being compelled
or drawn in or interested in what will
happen next um they've emphasized
focused attention so feelings of being
actively immersed in the experience to
the exclusion of um extra Musical stimul
and they've also pointed out that it has
you know seems to have temporal Dynamics
it's you know something that might
change throughout the listening
experience when we were looking a couple
of years ago or a year ago there wasn't
however any sort of theoretical account
of of the factors that are contributing
um to you know this continuous
experience over time and so um when
invited um we sort of to the special you
know contribute to the special issue um
we wondered what can we build a useful
framework of how things like curiosity
and attention and mind wandering May
emerge and you know um during the
context of music listening in order to
see if we could drive um research in
this area forward and just to sort of
give a few um fun fundamental claims
that we make in this in this paper well
we suggest for examp for a start that
our engagement with music is going is
cyclical it's going through you know
Peaks and troughs we're not always um
engaged Ed it's perfectly makes perfect
sense we are we find it very difficult
to not mind Wonder in any in any in any
context so it's not surprising that's
the case in music uh but certainly we
suggest that if there are moments of
people suddenly entering into heightened
attention or engagement with music it
might be because more music's just
started so there's a capacity to see if
there's anything to be learned or
interesting way to um yeah um but it
could also be moments Within the Music
um that are moments of high surprise and
what was have been up to then a quite
predictable context or even low surprise
and sort of more unpredictable context
because that can be just as um yeah
interesting for an agent um we suggest
that as I've said if there's Peaks
there'll be troughs the moments of
Engagement these moments of Engagement
will be interspersed with mind wandering
moments of Mind wandering which could be
explained by the redundancies in the
music that preclude any sort of
curiosity related Behavior or
attentional gain um
and then we you know I think one of the
most crucial claims is that you know
when we refocus on music after mind
wondering it could be because of what's
happening in the music um something that
may have you know um led to attentional
gain or um or sort of uh curiosity
things to um yeah the novelty or the the
fact that we there's something we don't
quite understand uh but it could also be
because um you know our capacity for
meta awareness has allowed us to see
that we're no longer attending and um
has allowed us to you know carry out
this mental action where we we we
reattend and last but not least just to
say that um again a claim of ours is
that as is the case for most music
listening um experiences um the level of
Engagement will be in and changes in
these levels of Engagement over time
will be modulated by complexity of
what's being heard so overall complexity
will determine how engaged we are in the
first place but also so um within um
within that if we are in a very
predictable piece section of the music
and suddenly something more complex
happens you know that's likely to induce
C you know curiosity or sort of more
attention compared to where conversely
if something's very unpredictable and um
you know something more simple and
predict and um unsurprising may be what
actually triggers are our interest and
engagement so basically saying that umit
like I alluded to earlier um
it's not as simple as complex or sort of
surprising will always trigger um
interest and engagement it's quite it
can be quite nuanced um but yeah also
saying we also you know argued that
expertise of course plays play a role um
because every person everyone will have
their own generative model in the case
of someone who has lots of musical
expertise this might be a very um
refined and sophisticated generative
model that allows them to make better
predictions um and tolerate the UN
uncertainty or entropy that might exist
in the piece of music at that moment and
last but not least we'd argue that the
listening situation the context really
matters um tells determines whether or
not we have the capacity to deploy
attention um to the music instead of say
I don't know um announcements being made
about the train that we are hoping to
get on in the next five minutes or so um
so just to summarize what I've said
today um the question was what is behind
this drive we seem to have as humans to
engage with music and I gave a sort of
an account that has come out of the work
that's being done in sort of the
neurosciences of Music where you know we
started looking at music perception we
we looked at pleasure and we're
beginning to a musical reward and we're
beginning to tease or put together a
story about how um pleasure is can be
explained by these frontal Temple con
connections um that are interfacing with
reward Network I think what quite nice
um is that um we're sort of seeing the
work that's been done in animal models
showing that information can be a reward
and beginning to try to
conceptualize um yeah music a little bit
in these terms you know where perhaps s
it's been suggested perhaps a centy
prediction era is beginning to become a
uh something that can actually result in
a reward prediction era which would of
course make it easier to interface our
perceptual systems with our reward
systems in a way that isn't always
immediately obvious with
with music a very abstract stimulus um
I've also provided sort of or reviewed
some of the predi predictive coding
literature or act of inference
literature that I found really um
compelling as I try to understand um
what might drive um changes in our
engagement with music over time try to
see how you know using this one
um um principle you could explain lots
of different behaviors we know are
probably going on as we engage with a
piece of music and just
not so much suggesting that pleasure is
a consequence but you know suggesting
that it's part of several different
processes it's not the only reason we
choose to engage even though we might
learn that music is pleasurable um but
we engage with for all these other
reasons
first um and just to say that you know
these are accounts that are very much um
increasingly converging lots of the work
we do in the neurosciences and when for
example I'm doing it it's not again work
I do but when I'm doing it I definitely
have an eye on what's coming of you know
this literature and likewise I think um
you know several people active in this
are working together with neurosciences
I think there clearly you know it's
increasingly converging I think there's
still a lot of work that needs to be
done to link some of the optimization
processes we you know we hear talked
about in that literature with the neural
substrates and processes that we are
able to um look at with um um in sort of
Neuroscience and music studies um but
the hope is that if we um start putting
forward some Frameworks
that
um are more closely informed by by this
literature perhaps the more we can drive
empirical work uh that can get us closer
to these you know accounts really not
just converging but being you know
really overlapping and helping um us
understand this question which is yeah
what is behind the human drive to engage
with music so I'll stop talking I don't
know how long it's been but I'm looking
forward to thoughts and
discussion awesome thank
you what is behind the human drive to
engage with
music so I think um a desire to um learn
about the world that we're in or is he a
desire just
um a need to to to improve our model of
the world um I think this is rewarded um
and
music we very quickly learned is a way
to learn and be rewarded at the same
time and it became something that um we
do you know as much
as you know an average you know a fifth
of our our waking hours um yeah it's
quite
a a lofty question but I would argue
it's at some point we learn that music
is rewarding and that's why we turn it
on but I'll say
ultimately um so is food and I don't
know there's lots of other rewards
something special about music and I
think it's this unfolding of abstract
information that somehow um you know can
capture our attention perhaps distract
us from other concerns that are more um
basic and yeah still somehow reward us
for that
distraction wow very inter interesting
like it has both a element of
pragmatic value especially like songs
from our childhood or a period that
we're familiar with listening to the
same exact recording or to a cover song
or to some other uh version or like a
live version there's sort of a
familiarity which can be like a
pragmatism and or pragmatic value and
then also your you're really getting
into the epistemic value and the fact it
is
learning and then there's so much
variation like what genre what song do
you listen to new music is it an uh
playlist assembled by an algorithm is it
something that somebody recommended to
you there's like so many layers of
learning even if it's a simple
sound yeah I think so I think that's
what's interesting about music you can
sort of study what's going on as people
are listening but you can also
study their actions their behaviors what
they go to see um what they choose to
listen to um what they buy what they're
willing spend their money on um and we
with curiosity is a just an idea we
explored it also with regard to what
people
um we've sort of looked not just as at
curiosity as a state but as a as a trait
and um shown
some shown that actually yes generally
being someone who's trait curious who
will seek out new experiences explains
you
know how much you'll report enjoying Med
that you've never heard before from a
culture you've never heard before and so
on and so forth so I guess um that was a
bit of an the side I guess there's a lot
of individual differences um and um when
we see people talk about Say musical
anhedonia it's really not a disorder
they're very quick to stress that it's a
sort of spectrum you can derive a lot of
pleasure from music um and be hyper
hedonic or you could be an anhedonic who
derives none um but but I guess that's
just an example of huge amount of
individual differences in our
experiences um and you know other more
General um traits some people talk about
personality trait like openness will
also predict how much we will show these
kinds of more exploratory Behavior or
how much we'll just exploit the music
that we know really
well I was really struck by the
definition of curiosity that you used
something like uncertainty we feel we
can resolve with action not just to to
know that we don't know is sort of a
condition of curiosity or it's a a
relative of curiosity but but to know we
don't know or to feel we don't know and
that we could do something active to
epistemically forage and then music is a
special situation where the action that
you can take it's like what will happen
in this techno beat drop will it be two
measures or will it be four but the
action to take is to
wait so it doesn't require another th
over body action or a mental attentional
action other than just to attend and to
let it
unfold so it plays out in time with
curiosity with sort of like a passive
action choice choice not to act not to
turn it off in a way that other
information reducing situations they're
they're modeled as like going out of
your way to do something to resolve
uncertainty yeah that's a great point I
think there's lots of um
paradigms um well the best par some of
the best paradigms for looking at
curiosity is you know how much you're
willing to spend time pay you know
attent to pay attention um to actually
find out um what's going to happen to
acquire that knowledge and exactly right
I think um one could build and I just
haven't got round to paradigms where
you're looking at just how much people
are willing to keep listening um instead
of switch over
you know almost as was the radio um yeah
people also looked at exerting effort
but this tend to be more
artificial um um yeah they've use these
kind of paradigms to see just how much
you're willing to do to to get that
information but I agree yeah we don't
have many overt actions that are um
observable with um listening to music
other than just not turning it off
um yeah and and that point
towards this extended engagement like
certainly from Little Snippets of Sound
and
Music certain aspects of listening and
attention can be explored but then
there'd be other dynamics that would
only start to come into play like over
multiple minutes like multiple
songs like I'm thinking about being at a
concert we're curious what song they're
going to play late in the set or if
they'll do an
encore also though
we prefer to go to bed early so there's
more traffic it's getting late so then
it's like that's a revealed stay or
go of how much do we want to resolve the
uncertainty as another cost starts to
another tradeoff starts to build up so
that's happening at a slower level than
like Rhythm detection over a 3 second
sliding window yeah definitely and I
think that's where it gets really
interesting and quite complex um I like
the literature coming out about um how
curiosity is contagious and you know
that you know this idea of the social
aspects
of information foraging or or you know
caring about information so with regard
to you know why you stick around and
don't leave maybe it's so you have the
complete picture of what that concert um
actually how it's turned out and you
want to be able to share that or you
certainly don't want to miss it um other
people are sticking around so you know
you're thinking well maybe they're right
this is something to to to stick around
for and yeah I think all of those
different
levels probably interacting I guess if
you got lots of boring tracks towards
the end you might be more inclined to
throw on the towel and leave before it
gets really bad traff to be yeah really
bad traffic but um yeah ultimately it'll
also depend on your your individual
differences and that at that point I'm
just sort of um need for cognition or
you know knowing everything but also
yeah other other things how much you
want to get your money's
worth
yeah another interesting piece was the
the two
streams so that had a lot of
similarities in the presentation with
the visual what and where yeah and it
was almost like there was a what and a
when so maybe could you restate that or
how does that when this come into play
or how is that separated out from an
essentially temporal
process yeah so um yeah very um simply
yeah it's very much borrowing from what
um had been put forward in the visual
domain and lots of music re re
Neuroscience research has you know
borrowed from what's gone on in Vision
the vision Sciences or Vision
neurosciences um and yeah the the sort
of what um pathway is this ventral
pathway um in the case of um the
auditory system it's the areas the house
the auditory
cortices um feeding into the inferior
temporal aerior frontal areas where
which are generally involved in sequence
sequencing and storing sequences and
using those to to make predictions as to
what the next um event and the sequence
might be in any given any given sequence
so that's the what predicting what's
going to happen and you know sending
predictions down the hierarchy about
what yeah what that might be with the
when music isn't just you know what's
happening it's when it's happening and
um um and so the when Paradigm this
dorsal um sorry the when pathway this is
the dorsal stream that's um
seeing um information travel between
these again cor auditory areas in the
superior temporal dyus and more motor
and parial areas um that are involved
have been shown to be involved in sort
of temporal processing so lots I didn't
show much work on Rhythm or me to
processing because I tended to work in
in pitch and that's why I meant by
sometimes of can be very reduced it's
because we just want to say look at
probabilities in the pitch domain before
we you know complicate by adding lots of
temporal information but yeah if someone
were to review that literature with you
um you'd see that um motor areas are
very much involved in our processing of
time in music and so this dorsal pathway
is basically doing everything from
helping us predict when something might
happen in a piece of music to um helping
us yeah uh well yeah predict when
something might happen but even helping
us make trans formations or auditory
motor um or or experience sort
of the motoric actions that could be
seen to be attached to that listening
experience so if you're a musician
knowing exactly um it underlies um the
sort
of Bly experiences of the movements you
might make even though you're not making
those movements so um the action you
know observation literature and their
neuron system and so on so these two
streams are clearly very important for
um just processing sound as musical
sounds as they evolve but um
interestingly in this um book I
mentioned um where um robor is trying to
put lots of things together he makes
this interesting observation which is
that um the dorsal
stream might be talking more to the
dorsal striatum which is involved in the
anticipation of which again is this kind
of like you're waiting for something
when am I going to get this extremely
rewarding moment that is the I know
modulation or the drop um and that you
know um prediction about what that drop
is going to be is meant to be observed
by the ventral system which um he you
know they've shown in a number of lots
of different studies is um almost
related more to this
ventral strim so yeah it's I think it
needs to be a little bit more
carefully
um yeah studied but um it's just another
way in which um there been people are
making attempts to try to understand how
the perceptual system um might be
interfacing with the um our reward
systems in a way that we you know we can
see um
anatomically um presented in in our
brains how are you seeing being AI
analysis and generation of Music
changing our understandings and habits
and behaviors and
listenings I I don't know actually I I
don't know
much there is I I spot um more and more
not surprisingly um papers or talks on
this around this topic I mean AI is
impacting so many aspects of Our Lives I
think even before
AI there was streaming there was lots
and lots of music that we could um
expose ourselves to it could just play
the whole day compared to you know when
we would have to buy CDs and I don't
know turn them on and so on so I think
there's some interesting behaviors
perhaps that have already begun to
emerge as we had more and more access to
music I think you know what's
interesting about AI is that you know
might in some cases
very little human um very few humans
involved and I and I think you know
there's some papers out there already
published I want to say
2007 but it could be 14 at least 10 if
not 15 years ago um that that have shown
that if you thought you were listening
to a piece of music that had been
composed by um an algorithm you showed a
lot less um activity in the theory of
mind Network as if you thought this
piece of music had been composed by a
composer so they stimul there were um
sort of atonal sort of Serial serialist
compositions which seemed plausible you
know um um composed by an algorithm um
and also by a composer now of course AI
is very convincing and it'll be
interesting I think I will be harder
maybe to detect or tell whether or not a
human was involved very hard indeed
but I think um my suggestion is that
once we recognize that um there wasn't
really a human involved we might
show a drop in engagement with and that
in that sort of social way that music
can be engaging where we try to
understand what the artist is trying to
tell us where we want to feel with the
performer And the emotions they're
expressing um without that
recognition I you know I think with just
listening to music and we'll engage you
know to the extent that we find it
interesting or stimulating or or
pleasurable regardless of yeah where it
came
from yeah that's interesting it's almost
like the ability to generate images
sounds Etc is helping to to articulate
out what are the aspects of this image
that have a
primary
saliency like WEA for pragmatic value
aligning with what we' like to see or
hear or the epistemic the learning and
then separating or factoring that off
from the social and the relational like
this drawing was made by this person so
I like to look at it it has a
saliency um and also those pragmatic and
epistemic elements
not only from its actual
composition but because there's like
more knowledge about the generative
process that led to to its
construction so then that those paths
May diverge more and more as like new
genres of very Salient music like I
thought about on your plot with the
affect are there genres or or
subcultures in their listening of genres
that it's just like it Stacks all the
positive aects and then that made me
think a little bit about the sped up
mashup
remixes that change songs and they it's
like songs and Nostalgia at a very very
fast interesting rate and so it's like
it's just like a few not notes to invoke
something and then on to the next
one and it just this kind of moving on
through novelty and
Nostalgia yeah and what you do and don't
know and it's kind of like it's so
compressed and trying to have every part
be really hyped up and then other pieces
that maybe like considered from the
album
composition might have like a slow
song that's not trying to be so salience
even or it's giving a contrast that sets
something else up more
deeply yeah yeah no I yeah it's I love
that I love the sort of mash up just
like yeah feed me all this Nostalgia I
think that's so there's our interest in
feeling with the other in Fong empathy
that's meant to you know it suggested
that actually it's a fact that the word
for empathy came out of how we described
our experiences of the art with feeling
into yeah so there's this social um
aspect to listening um people talk about
surrogate um or just this idea even if
we don't there isn't anyone there if
it's just a recording we're listening
with our headphones on on the tube um we
still imagine this person there's that
but I think the Nostalgia is really
interesting because we're almost
like empathizing with our previous s and
our feelings and emotions there which
have been so which music is so able to
bring back to us you know what our what
our priorities and our values were in
those you know those stages when we were
listening or just you know what fun
times or who we were hanging out with at
those moments so I think yeah that's
that's really interesting I mean and
like you said is really trying to do is
trying to really tap
into this desire we have to use music to
connect with ourselves yeah and then yes
something that's really slow goinging
you know very
minimalist really does set you up then
to find the
most tiny deviation extremely Salient
and interesting and worthy of pondering
or just exploring that experience and
they're very different things and I
think we'll um we'll seek the these
kinds of music out at different you know
moments um in our day in our
lives um some of some music will just
constant will completely will capture
and you know hold your attention you
know we we seen with this idea of the
attention economy where um uh yeah we
only have so much attention to to share
amongst the things that might compete
for our attention and um people use that
to look at how you know how that might
have been
influencing how this principle might be
influencing how music is composed um and
has been composed popular music in the
last you know 50 or so years and shown
you know music is louder you know the
hook comes in quicker um and you know
and so on and so forth um so that's you
know an example
of this tendency for some composers to
try to hold um to capture and hold our
attention because it's so easy to just
click next on Spotify um where yeah
others conversely probably are trying
to react against that or their aesthetic
values that music should never be that
engaging and there should be time to
ruminate or just to follow the form you
know for as long as you know um you'd
like without having to process the next
thing and then the next thing and then
the next thing
um yeah different affordances I guess
that music has for any any
listener yeah that's very like media is
the message for a record to begin with
10 or 30 seconds of silence or the slow
buildup when there's already like the
few extra seconds of just the record
tracking it's not like you're going to
switch the song but then if there is a
way if it's a playlist having 10 or 30
seconds in the song at the beginning or
the
end it might not be played like in a
public space or on a run where you might
be expecting continuous music and then
that changes the the technical culture
of
listening and and again that's related
to this extended engagement building on
the pitch and the Rhythm identification
there's still these questions about
longer
term listening it's kind of like the
dark
room how well okay if we're bounding
surprise why not the dark room Etc not
to go into this but it's like but what
about the movie theater room or what
about the uh sound Listening
Room it it's it's like a little bit of
an it's a uh enliven
room it has stimuli and then those are
the situations that the extended
engagement is looking into how long do
you stay playing a video game or
listening to music or playing
music when other things could happen and
then it's not just an inner analysis of
Music it does start to invoke like well
you can't just do this for 24 hours so
there has to be some stopping time where
even the most
passionate uh person is still going to
like take a break or something like
that yeah yeah and I think what's
interesting is you know most times we
hope we have that ability to decide when
to stop and maybe we can prepare
ourselves or tell ourselves we can do
this tomorrow um as well or or Savor the
experience so um you know whenever I've
watched a moving movie in the theater
most time times I'll just sit and watch
the credits and listen um and just kind
of
reflect um it's very um annoying when
you watch a movie on some of these um
Netflix and before they've even done a
few seconds of the closing credits they
they're advertising the next I think um
we probably have learned
to you know this savoring of what we've
just experienced and you know letting it
tail off in a way that's um
yeah we can manage as opposed to it
suddenly being rudely interrupted and I
think that's probably why we can you
know even the most passionate listeners
is able to turn it off and be like okay
now I actually have to get some work
done or now I have to you know good bit
um because we can manage that tailing
off most times if we're lucky yeah and
the space within and at the end as a
kind of
inculturation like in classical music
there'll be a pause nobody will clap or
you'll hear one person clap it's like oh
no but then at the end and then clapping
it's a motor a a joint motor activity
that signals okay it's really the
end and so then that there's like you
you mentioned um the
expertise increased the focus and the
the epistemic component possibly if for
nothing else like I want to see how this
book ends I want to see how I want to
see how the structural elements and what
I've heard so far relate to How It
Ends so it's like all because of
knowledge of the structural form or the
genre of the murder mystery or the this
kind of song that kind of
song there can be a structural
curiosity that keeps one engaged
even separate from any other kind of
curiosity just like as a craft how will
the author do this how did the composer
bring this all to a close and then that
gives this epistemic um
Arc that that is informed by the genre
yeah I'm reminded that
um the study where I stud I keep saying
study imp peral work or the the paper
where um first colleagues talk about
sort of Act of inference and curiosity
and they actually talk about insights as
well and talk about sort of how even
without extra information sort of just
restructuring what you what you've
acquired what you've learned can lead to
these moments of insight and I guess
when I'm sitting there taking in
everything I've you know just read you
know nothing worse than reading a book
and then having
to it and you know go off and do
something you know not having that
moment to sort of think some more and I
think it's because
there's probably insights to be gain
only after you've come to that Final End
which I'm sure was carefully crafted by
whoever you know created the work
and yeah just time to process further
and you know gain some further Insight
um there is that yeah what's happening
during the artwork but there's time
that's
needed
to to establish what was actually
learned
you know once everything had come
together and it makes me think about the
John Cage type concepts of Music being
time time bound whereas a painting or
visual
art it doesn't have a constraint so much
or so similar on time the museum
Observer could be there for a split
second or for a long time
but then there's a time boundness so
it's sort of like well there's um a
canvas of just one color and then that
is like the
433 song that's a duration oh there's
nothing there oh well there's the
Ambient sound and there's the structural
element
voided of traditional contents just like
the canvas kind of cleared of its
traditional content
content and then how how those kind
works like explore limits of art
however I don't have blank canvases
around me most people don't listen to
433 um when they're going for a run yeah
so it's there still is is preference
distributions overlaid it's not just
about having like this this um genre
defining like meta art piece there's
also just like the normal day-to-day um
yeah yeah I mean I think that's where
people talk about the context so um yeah
you need that work needs to be in a
museum or a gallery um or in a concert
as the case may be um people talk about
the aesthetic attitude and distance or
um I
think there's that element of yeah the
extent to which you
can deploy cognitive resources to
this not extremely urgent problem um and
there very few situations or
circumstances where you can just sorry
in daily life where you have that time
to um to do that and so setting is so
important in addition to these
individual differences and you know how
much we want to spend our time doing
that that sort of
thing cool well what are your next moves
or what are your directions for research
with music or for
anything
[Music]
um I've always yeah I got to sort of
work in very Neuroscience places and
other places that were do Neuroscience
but we care about these lofty questions
around the atic experience um so and I I
at some point I got interested in I
think starting with surprise and you
know just electrophysiological responses
to those how that you know could lead to
curiosity this you know extended
engagement but I I guess I've been
interested in other EP barely epistemic
emotions so
um uh or is one that we've been
exploring
recently
um uh with students um and the reason is
um well it's one of those emotions that
are very hard to pin down as an
experimental
uh we're going to try to use we've been
trying to use um VR to create more
naturalistic settings that people might
hear music or and even then begin to
compare what all induced by music might
look like compared to all induced by I
don't know nature or the visual world
and so on um and yeah trying to
understand a little bit more
about our desire for learning or
understanding how you know experiences
like Wonder can come out of abstract
stimula like um music and yeah really
bridge
this link or better understand this link
between knowledge seeking and
um aesthetic transcendental experiences
that we can have with with the art so
there's that kind of work being done and
yeah in other work we sort of look it
the images the music can canj up and I'm
really interested in you know
predictions or engagement at those
levels as well so in a way some of the
the accounts they've given today are
very much like oh and you care about the
next note and what's going to happen but
sometimes you're imagining yourself um
and others and personal memories are
mixed up with all of these you know um
thoughts that are more related to the
music as it unfolds and
inevitably um it'll be interesting to
understand a bit more about that level
of Engagement with music so we can see
how it's either explainable by some of
these principles or at least um needs to
be considered um
alongside
um yeah I think that's the most relevant
work that I'm doing planning on doing to
the work I presented
today cool well thank you very much for
joining super interesting and look
forward to talking again thank you so
much Daniel thanks bye e